Finding Aid for Prentiss Marsh Brown Papers 1902-1973
Bentley Historical Library, University of Michigan
Prentiss Marsh Brown Papers 1902-1973
Brown, Prentiss M. (Prentiss Marsh), 1889-1973.
Michigan congressman and senator, head of the U.S. Office of Price Administration; papers include correspondence, legislative files, speeches, political files, business and legal records, diaries and scrapbooks, visual materials, and sound recordings.
85837 Aa 2 Ac
28 linear feet in 29 boxes
2 oversize folders
12 microfilms
Bentley Historical Library University of Michigan
The collection was donated by Prentiss M. Brown (donor no. 4421 ) and his family (donor no. 5760 ) in three accessions in 1966 and 1975.
The collection is open for research.
Prentiss M. Brown was born at St. Ignace, Michigan on June 18, 1889. He was the son of James J. and Minnie Brown, his father having been at one time Detroit city attorney and later prosecuting attorney of Cheboygan and Mackinac counties. Brown was educated in the St. Ignace schools, graduating in 1906. He went to Albion College, graduating in 1911 with an A.B. degree. A scholarship in political economy attracted him to the University of Illinois where he worked from 1911 to 1914. In 1914 he returned to St. Ignace and commenced the practice of law with his father. In the fall of 1914, he was elected prosecuting attorney of Mackinac County on the Democratic ticket and was reelected for each succeeding term until 1926 when he voluntarily retired. In 1930 on the recommendation of the Supreme Court of Michigan he was appointed a member of the State Board of Law Examiners. He was reappointed in 1931 and again in 1936 (he declined reappointment in 1941).
In 1932 Brown was elected to the U.S. House of Representatives from the 11th District of Michigan, the first Democrat to be elected to Congress from that district. He was reelected in 1934 running approximately 10,000 votes ahead of his ticket. During his service in the House of Representatives, Brown was a member of one of its most important committees: Banking and Currency. Due to the banking crisis of 1933, this probably was the most vital committee in the House of Representatives in the first three years of the Roosevelt Administration. As a member of that important committee, he helped draft the legislation establishing many of the recovery agencies of the Government created to combat the depression. Some of these agencies are the Home Owners' Loan Corporation, the Banking Acts of 1933 and 1935 (including Federal Deposit Insurance). Brown was also active in the enactment of the legislation creating the Civilian Conservation Corps and several of the farm credit agencies which were under jurisdiction of the Banking Committee. In addition, Brown was a member of the first congressional committee created by House resolution to investigate duplication of Executive agencies.
Brown was elected to the Senate on November 3, 1936. Soon after his election, with the death of James Couzens, Brown was appointed to fill that unexpired term and so took office a few weeks early. Brown was chosen chairman of the 1938 Democratic Senatorial Campaign Committee, also chairman of the Senate Special Committee on Taxation of Governmental Securities and Salaries, where he served from 1938 to 1940. In the Senate, Brown was chairman of the Senate Committee on Claims and a member of the following committees of the Senate: Finance, Banking and Currency, Commerce, Manufacturers, and Special Committee to Investigate Duplication of Executive Agencies of the Government. He was selected to be a member of the powerful Senate Democratic Steering Committee. This committee decides and directs the legislative program of the United States Senate and selects, as vacancies occur, Senators for appointment to the regular standing committees of the Senate.
In 1941, Brown was placed on the Commerce Committee. Also in 1941, he became chairman of the Senate Committee on Claims. As chairman of the Special Senate Committee on Taxation of Governmental Securities and Salaries, Brown was the sponsor of the legislation that brought about reciprocal taxation of salaries. Before, state employees were exempt from federal income tax, and federal employees exempt from state income taxes. Because of the legislation which Brown sponsored, all (both state and federal) were now subject to both taxes. In other words, state employees must pay the federal income tax and federal employees must pay the state income tax in states which have such a tax. His bill also imposed the income tax on all federal judges who had theretofore been exempt. Another piece of legislation which he sponsored did away with tax-exempt government securities. The income from federal government bonds is no longer exempt from taxation. For a long time the senator had advocated passage of legislation to tax the income from state, county, and municipal bonds. His amendment to the Tax Bill of 1939 sought to accomplish this, but was defeated by a narrow margin.
Brown had sponsored and acted as senate floor manager for most of the legislation broadening the lending authority of the Reconstruction Finance Corporation. The various corporations set up by the government to construct tank plants, gun plants, to build up rubber reserves, metal reserves, etc., were all created by legislation that Senator Brown sponsored in the Senate.
Brown also sponsored legislation continuing and broadening the Federal Housing Administration and was in charge of the price control legislation. He had been active in the work of the Senate Finance Committee and had been a vital factor in every tax bill written since 1936. He was in charge of the legislation authorizing issue of defense bonds and was insistent upon the inclusion in the Public Debt Bill of authority to sell bonds of small denominations, commonly known as baby bonds. This legislation was passed in March of 1941. His fight to enact a Price Control bill for the benefit of the American consumer had been highly commended by most informed authorities. Brown was chairman of the conference between the two houses of congress which put the bill in final shape.
Senator Brown was active in the "Aid to Small Business" bill. It came out of the Banking and Currency Committee, of which he was a member, and he was, as a member of the committee, active in support of the bill on the floor of the Senate. It provided for relief to small businesses through loans to assist them in getting work in the war program.
Senator Brown reported from the Banking and Currency Committee the bill entitled, "For the relief of dealers in certain articles or commodities rationed under authority of the United States." He also handled this bill on the Floor of the Senate and steered it to adoption by the Senate. This bill afforded relief to anyone dealing in rationed articles, but was primarily a measure of relief for the automobile and tire dealers who had been so adversely affected by the auto and tire curtailment.
Although he supported the Roosevelt Administration in its general policies, Senator Brown had by no means been a "yes" man in his service in Congress. Among the more important measures with which he had taken issue with the Administration was the following: the proposal to increase the membership of the Supreme Court; the first proposal to reorganize the Executive agencies of the Government; and the proposal to place the Civil Aeronautics Authority under the Commerce Department. Chief credit for defeat of the proposal to pack the Supreme Court was given to Senator Brown by Joseph Alsop and Turner Catledge, chief correspondents for the New York Herald Tribune and the New York Times respectively.
The Senator's opposition to the Reorganization Bill was based on his belief that it gave legislative authority to the executive. He proposed a compromise which was rejected. It is commonly said that the rejection of this compromise caused the defeat of the bill. Subsequently, the bill was reintroduced with Senator Brown's amendment which left final authority in the congress, although giving the President primary authority. The bill as amended was then passed.
Brown ran for re-election in 1942, but was narrowly defeated by Homer Ferguson. He attributed his defeat to two things. First, his sponsorship of the OPA Act had made elements within business and industry extremely unhappy. Price fixing and rationing in particular had upset a lot of people, especially within the business community. Second, the small voter turnout in the 1942 election was below average. The nation was at war; the voter turnout was light, particularly among the working classes; the Democrats simply did not go to the polls.
After the election, President Roosevelt selected Brown as the new administrator of the Office of Price Administration. He worked in this position from January to October of 1943, and only then returned to Michigan to pick up the threads of his law practice and many business interests. In 1944, Brown was elected chairman of the board of the Detroit Edison Company, a position he held until his retirement in 1954.
In some ways, Brown's "retirement" years were his most rewarding. Long a proponent of a bridge uniting Michigan's two peninsulas, Brown, as chairman of the Mackinac Bridge Authority, worked long and hard to obtain the necessary financing for the Bridge. In 1954, in what he always considered his greatest achievement, Brown received from the Union Securities Corporation a check for 96 million dollars. Construction began soon thereafter; and on November 1, 1957, the Mackinac Bridge opened for traffic. Brown spent the remainder of his life in bridge related activities, business affairs, and historical pursuits.
Brown was married June 16, 1916, to Marion E. Walker of St. Ignace, a graduate of Michigan State College. They had seven children: Mariana F., Ruth M., James J., Barbara J., Patricia J., Prentiss M., Jr., and Paul W.
Senator Brown died on December 19, 1973.
Wherever possible, the materials are preserved in the order maintained by Brown and his staff in St. Ignace and Washington. With the series of political papers, speeches, and legislative case files, this presented no problem. With other materials, however, an arrangement system had to be imposed since the materials came to the library unarranged. These papers were sorted chronologically and placed into a Correspondence series (boxes #1-3). Though such material might originally have belonged to one of the established series in Brown's filing system, it was unclear which was the appropriate category. Rather than disrupting the integrity of the other series, therefore, this unordered material was put into its own separate series. When processing was completed, the collection comprised twelve different series.
The Prentiss M. Brown Collection is rich and full and offers researchers materials on a variety of local and national topics reflecting the diversity of the man's private and public life. The earliest item in the collection is a letter book dated 1902-04 of James J. Brown, like his son a prominent St. Ignace attorney. The collection then picks up Prentiss M. Brown's entrance to the legal profession in 1917, traces his rise to public office, his work in Congress and with the O.P.A., and then concludes with his later business interests and his crusade upon behalf of the Mackinac Bridge.
The Brown Collection comprises approximately twenty-eight feet of correspondence, letterbooks, scrapbooks, diaries, speeches, topical and legislative files, photographs and phonograph records, and legal case files and business records. Covering the period 1917 to 1973, the papers concentrate most heavily in the years 1932-1942 when Brown was in the U.S. Congress. The greatest gap in the collection is in the period of the 1920s when Brown was making his first bids for political office. Also missing are any extensive files for the time of Brown's O.P.A. directorship. What the collection has on the O.P.A. are largely speeches, scrapbooks, and congratulatory letters.
Subjects:
Banks and banking--Michigan.; Arnold Transit Company.; Bridges--Michigan.; Brown, Prentiss M. (Prentiss Marsh), 1889-1973.; Democratic Party (Mich.); Depressions--1929--United States.; Ferries--Michigan.; Mackinac Bridge Authority (Mich.); Mackinac Island (Mich.); Mackinac Island (Mich.)--Businesses.; Michigan. Mackinac Straits Bridge Authority.; New Deal, 1933-1939.; Saint Ignace (Mich.); Taxation--United States.; United States. Congress--Elections, 1938.; United States. Congress--Elections, 1940.; United States. Congress--Elections, 1942.; United States. Congress. House.; United States. Congress. Senate.; United States. Office of Price Administration.; United States--Politics and government--1929-1933.; United States--Politics and government--1933-1945.; World War, 1939-1945.
Subjects - Visual Material:
Albion College.; Arnold Transit Company.; Brown, James J.; Brown, Prentiss M. (Prentiss Marsh), 1889-1973.; City Hall (Detroit, Mich.); Dodd, Thomas J. (Thomas Joseph), 1907-1971.; Douglas, Paul H. (Paul Howard), 1892-1976; Freeman, Orville L.; Gore, Albert, 1907-1998.; Harriman, W. Averell (William Averell), 1891-1986.; Humphrey, Hubert H. (Hubert Horatio), 1911-1978.; Javitz, Jacob K. (Jacob Koppel), 1904-; Kefauver, Estes, 1903-1963.; Kennedy, Edward M. (Edward Moore), 1932-2009; Legislators--United States.; Long, Edward V. (Edward Vaughn), 1908-1972; McNamara, Patrick Vincent, 1894-1966.; Mackinac Bridge (Mich.); Mackinac Island (Mich.); Mansfield, Mike, 1903-2001; Mackinac Bridge Authority (Mich.); Moss, Frank E., 1911-2003; Offices.; Proxmire, William.; Rostow, W. W. (Walt Whitman), 1916-2003; Saint Ignace (Mich.); Saltonstall, Leverett, 1892-1979; Ships--Great Lakes.; Shriver, Sargent, 1915-2011; Tufty, Esther Van Wagoner, d. 1986.; Udall, Stewart L.; United States. Congress. Senate.; United States. Office of Price Administration.
Contributors:
Abbott, Horatio J. (Horatio Johnson), 1876-1936; Andrews, Roger, 1874-; Averill, George R., 1893-1971.; Avery, Sewell Lee, 1873-1960.; Barkley, Alben William, 1877-1956.; Bell, Jack L., 1904-; Bennett, Harry Herbert, 1892-1979.; Byrnes, James Francis, 1879-1972.; Cady, Claude Ernest, 1878-1953.; Cleary, Gerald J.; Comstock, William Alfred, 1877-1949.; Couzens, Frank, 1902-1950.; Couzens, James, 1872-1936.; Debo, Alfred.; DeFoe, Murl Holcomb, 1879-; Diggs, Charles C.; Dingell, John D. (John David), 1894-1955.; Downey, Sheridan.; Eccles, Marriner S. (Marriner Stoddard), 1890-1977.; Farley, James A. (James Aloysius), 1888-1976.; Fead, Louis H., 1877-1943.; Fenlon, Edward H.; Fitzgerald, Frank Dwight, 1885-1939.; Garner, John Nance, 1868-1967.; Gomon, Josephine Fellows, 1892-1975.; Green, Fred W. (Fred Warren), 1872-1936.; Guffey, Joseph F., 1870-1959.; Hatch, Carl A., 1889-1963.; Hatfield, Malcolm Keith, 1900-1961.; Henderson, Leon, 1895-1986; Hook, Frank Eugene, 1893-1982.; Hoover, J. Edgar (John Edgar), 1895-1972.; Hull, Cordell, 1871-1955.; Hurja, Emil, 1892-; Jackson, Robert Houghwout, 1892-1954.; James, William Francis, 1873-1945.; Jones, Jesse H. (Jesse Holman), 1874-1956.; Kennedy, G. Donald (George Donald), 1900-1988; Kimmerle, Charles H., 1860-; Kresge, Sebastian Spering, 1867-1966.; Lederle, Arthur F., 1887-; Lehr, John Camillus, 1878-1958.; Luecke, John, 1889-1952.; McAllister, Thomas Francis, 1896-; McKay, Frank, 1883-1965.; Mershon, Wm. B. (William Butts), 1856-1943.; Morgenthau, Henry, 1856-1946.; Murphy, Frank, 1890-1949.; Musselwhite, Harry Webster, 1868-1955.; Norris, George W. (George William), 1861-1944.; Osborn, Chase S. (Chase Salmon), b. 1860.; Osborn, Stellanova, 1894-1988.; Picard, Frank A., 1889-1963.; Reichert, Rudolph Edward, 1887-1965.; Roosevelt, Franklin D. (Franklin Delano), 1882-1945.; Shields, Edmund Claude, 1871-1947.; Smith, Gerald L. K. (Gerald Lyman Kenneth), 1898-1976; Smith, Shirley Wheeler, 1875-1959.; Spence, Brent, 1874-1967.; Stack, John K., 1884-1935.; Starr, Raymond Wesley, 1888-1968.; Steagall, Henry Bascom, 1873-1943.; Toms, Robert Morrell, 1886-1960.; Treanor, Arthur Ryan, 1883-1956.; Truman, Harry S., 1884-1972.; Vandenberg, Arthur H. (Arthur Hendrick), 1884-1951.; Van Wagoner, Murray Delos, 1898-; Wagner, Robert F. (Robert Ferdinand), 1877-1953.; Welsh, George Wilson, 1883-1974.; White, Walter Francis, 1893-1955.; Woodfill, W. Stewart, b. 1896.
Genre/Form:
Caricatures.; Cartoons.; Diaries.; Photographs.; Scrapbooks.; Sound recordings.; Videotapes.
- Biographical/family
  The collection begins with a small series of Biographical/Family Material about the life and career of Prentiss M. Brown. These folders of course should be supplemented with detailed information about Brown to be found in the Scrapbook and Clippings series. The series also includes a small folder of earlier family correspondence.
  - Biographical material, 4 folders (Box 1)
  - Family correspondence (Box 1)
- Correspondence 1930-1973, 2.5 linear feet
  The Correspondence series (2.5 linear ft.; 1930-1973) is made up of a mixture of legislative and business papers, letters from constituents, and personal correspondence. To aid the researcher, this series has been intensively indexed for significant correspondents. Noteworthy individuals in these files include politicians, public figures, and business people. Some of Brown's correspondents are: Horatio J. Abbott, Roger M. Andrews, George R. Averill, Sewell Avery, Alben W. Barkley, Jack L. Bell, Harry H. Bennett, James F. Byrnes, Claude E. Cady, Gerald J. Cleary, William A. Comstock, Frank Couzens, James J. Couzens, Alfred Debo, Murl H. DeFoe, Charles C. Diggs, John D. Dingell, Sheridan Downey, Marriner S. Eccles, James A. Farley, Louis H. Fead, Edward H. Fenlon, Frank D. Fitzgerald, John N. Garner, Josephine Gomon, Fred W. Green, Joseph F. Guffey, Carl A. Hatch, Malcolm K. Hatfield, Leon Henderson, Frank E. Hook, J. Edgar Hoover, Cordell Hull, Emil E. Hurja, Robert H. Jackson, William F. James, Jesse Holman Jones, George D. Kennedy, Charles H. Kimmerle, Sebastian S. Kresge, Arthur F. Lederle, John C. Lehr, John Luecke, Thomas F. McAllister, Frank D. McKay, William B. Mershon, Henry Morgenthau, Frank Murphy, Hary W. Musselwhite, George W. Norris, Chase S. Osborn, Stella B. Osborn, Frank A. Picard, Rudolph E. Reichert, Franklin D. Roosevelt, Edmund C. Shields, Gerald L.K. Smith, Shirley W. Smith, Brent Spence, John K. Stack, Raymond W. Starr, Henry B. Steagall, Robert M. Toms, Arthur R. Treanor, Harry S Truman, Arthur H. Vandenberg, Murray D. Van Wagoner, Robert F. Wagner, George W. Welsh, Walter F. White, and W.S. Woodfill.
  - Undated 1930-June 1937, 53 folders (Box 1)
  - July 1937-1953, 58 folders (Box 2)
  - 1954-1973, 38 folders (Box 3)
- Political files 1934-1956, 2 linear feet
  The Political files series (2 linear ft.; 1934-1956) consists of correspondence and campaign miscellanea documenting Brown's political activities in the period of 1934 to 1942. There is significant material here on the election campaigns of 1940 and 1942 and on Brown's work with the Democratic Senatorial Campaign Committee in 1938.
  - 1934-1941
    - Certificate of election 1934 (Folder Ac)
    - Appointment to the U.S. Senate 1936 (Folder Ac)
    - Campaign papers 1934-1939 (Box 3)
    - Democratic Senatorial Campaign Committee
      - Correspondence 1938, 4 folders (Box 3)
      - Financial material and newspaper clippings (Box 3)
      - Campaign miscellanea (Box 3)
    - Spring election January-April 1939, 2 folders (Box 3)
    - Campaign papers 1940, 6 folders (Box 3)
    - Campaign lists, 2 folders (Box 3)
    - Campaign miscellanea (Box 3)
    - Campaign papers 1941, 2 folders (Box 3)
    - Campaign miscellanea 1941 (Box 3)
    - Democratic Senate Steering Committee 1941 (Box 3)
  - 1942 Campaign
    - Subject files
      - Independent Michigan Editors' Committee Supporting Senator Prentiss M. Brown (Box 4)
      - Republican opposition
        - Elton R. Eaton (Box 4)
        - Homer Ferguson (Box 4)
        - Gerald L.K. Smith, 2 folders (Box 4)
      - Offers of campaign help (Box 4)
      - Tally controversy, St. Clair County (Box 4)
      - Political bills paid 1942-1943 (Box 4)
      - Campaign contributors, 2 folders (Box 4)
      - Campaign checks returned (Box 4)
      - "The 1942 National Campaign in Michigan" (Box 4)
    - Dated files
      - Undated 1942, January 1942-October 28, 1942, 36 folders (Box 4)
      - October 29, 1942-December 1942, 3 folders (Box 5)
    - Miscellaneous
      - Campaign miscellanea (Box 5)
      - Campaign lists, schedules, and memos (Box 5)
      - Newspaper clippings (Box 5)
      - Financial material, 6 folders (Box 5)
  - Political papers 1954-1956 (Box 5)
- Legislative files 1933-1942
  The Legislative files series (1933-1942.; 1933-1942) includes Brown's voting record in Congress and the record of bills which he introduced. This Legislative series also contains a great deal of material on specific legislation. Such files have been sorted by term of Congress, then by session in that Congress, and finally by the bill number. Although many of these files are on private bills (e.g. naturalization cases, relief of widows of Civil War veterans, etc.), there is also important material here on tax and banking legislation, the Mackinac Straits Bridge legislation, and legislation to amend the Hatch Act. These Legislative files are strongest for the period of 1936 to 1942, essentially the late New Deal and early years of the Second World War. As a rule, these files include a copy of the particular legislation, drafts of the bill, correspondence on the issue, and perhaps some related supplementary material.
  - Voting Record
    - Important domestic legislation 1933-1941 (Box 5)
    - Military and nation defense legislation 1935-1941 (Box 5)
    - 75th Congress, 1st Session (Box 5)
    - 75th Congress, 2nd-3rd Session (Box 5)
    - 75th Congress, lst Session (Box 5)
    - 76th Congress, Special Session (Box 5)
    - 76th Congress, 3rd Session (Box 5)
    - 77th Congress, lst Session (Box 5)
  - Bills Introduced
    - 74th Congress (Box 5)
    - 75th Congress (Box 5)
    - 76th Congress, lst Session (Box 5)
    - 76th Congress, 3rd Session (Box 5)
    - 77th Congress, 4 folders (Box 5)
  - Legislation by topic
    - Transportation to Isle Royale National Park (Box 5)
    - Michigan Commemorative Half Dollar (Box 5)
    - Improvement of Crooked and Indian Rivers (Box 5)
    - Technical Administrative Tax Bill (Box 5)
    - Tax Legislation, 5 folders (Box 5)
    - Price Control Legislation, 3 folders (Box 5)
    - Auto financing: anti-trust action, 2 folders (Box 6)
    - Joint Congressional Committee on Forest Conditions (Box 6)
    - 1, 2, 3 National Steamship Co. Bill (Box 6)
    - War Production Board: Protection for Iron Ore Transportation (Box 6)
  - Mackinac Straits Bridge Legislation
    - Dated files 1933-1942, 10 folders (Box 6)
    - Supplementary material, 8 folders (Box 6)
  - Special Committee on Taxation of Governmental Securities and Salaries
    - Dated files May 1938-1942, 14 folders (Box 6)
    - Supplementary material, 8 folders (Box 6)
    - Supplementary material, 3 folders (Box 7)
  - Legislative files (Bills arranged by Congress, Session, and Number)
    - 72nd Congress, lst Session: H.R. 6198 Ross C. Ramsay (Box 7)
    - 74th Congress, lst Session
      - H.R. 1494, Improvement of Waiska River (Box 7)
      - H.R. 1498, Rosa Striebich (Box 7)
      - H.R. 7367, Receivers Attorney Fees (Box 7)
    - 75th Congress, lst Session
      - S. 1879, Reconstruction Finance Corporation and loans to cities, 3 folders (Box 7)
      - S. 2898, Airport bill (Box 7)
    - 75th Congress, 3rd Session
      - S. 1878, Mary Way (Box 7)
      - S. 3387, Hubert J. Cuncannan (Box 7)
      - S. 3388, U.S. Veterans Hospital for Gladstone, 3 folders (Box 7)
      - S. 3972, Liberty Bond Amendment (Box 7)